In the previous lesson,
we have learned that Cloud Foundry is an open-source PaaS.
That means that we'll be able to install it on any available infrastructure,
such as on-premises or public Cloud providers.
In this demo, we will see how can we use Cloud Foundry to deploy an application.
However, before we do that,
let's explore an offering of Cloud Foundry from SUSE.
In this view, we have the straightest console
which is a SUSE offering that runs Cloud Foundry.
This is the Developer Sandbox,
which we will be able to interact with to deploy an actual application.
I have created an account and once you're logged in to the console,
this is pretty much the VOC.
At the moment, we have done no actions and we
performed no operations within this console.
Let's go for some of the main functionalities
that these developer console is offering us.
If you look onto the left panel,
we'll see a list of operations or functionalities that we'll be able to use.
The first one is applications.
If you click on it, currently,
we said we have no obligations up and running in this particular console.
When we'll be able to create an application,
we'll be able to examine it from this view.
If I click on the "Marketplace," this will provide us with
a list of all the services we will be able to integrate with our application.
For example, here we have quite a rich collection of databases.
For example, we'll be able to choose from Mariadb, Mongodb,
Postgresql, Rabbitmq, and Redis,
and we'll be able to integrate those.
If I click on "Services," this will allow us to
view any services that we currently integrated with our application.
Currently, these view is empty.
However, if you choose a particular database to integrate with your application,
you'll be able to visualize this here.
The next step we want to click is actual Cloud Foundry.
This will provide us with a more insightful view of what Cloud Foundry
offers to us and how can manage our applications using Cloud Foundry.
In the first view, we're going to see the summary.
Here we'll be able to see for example,
the Cloud Foundry version.
Here is going to be in version 2.153.0.
We'll be able to see our instance address or
the endpoint that we can access the Cloud Foundry API.
You'll see the amount of applications that are running currently using Cloud Foundry.
Currently, there's going to be zero applications and we
can see the works and the used memory as well.
If you click on the "Organizations," this is going to provide us with
a view of how can you manage multi-tenancy using Cloud Foundry.
For example, my current account is a Manager and currently I'm running zero applications,
well actually, I have 10 instances that I'm eligible to deploy with these test account.
As well with an organization,
we can limit the amount of resources that we can consume.
For this particular organization,
we have only 2.5 gigabytes.
We'll be able to click on this particular user and we'll be able
to see a more insightful view for our organization.
Again, we have a summary where we have four spaces,
these are going to be our development stages.
The amount of applications,
the amount of fruits,
or up instances running.
If you click on the "Spaces," these are going to provide
us with the development stages that we currently have.
Here we can have Sandbox or dev, staging,
production and currently in this view have dev,
prod, samples, and test.
We can view all users.
If you click on the users,
we'll be able to visualize all of the users and
the axis that's provisioned for that particular user.
In this case, my account is provisioned with a manager role
which has privilege or a privilege access within this console.
The last thing I'd like to showcase is the Quota for an organization.
If you click on the "Quota," you'll be able to see the amount of memory
that we are allowed to use with this particular organization,
the amount of applications that we can deploy,
amount of services, routes, and so forth.
All of this information we'll be able to manage from this particular view.
Now let's go back to Cloud Foundry and let's go from organizations to our cells.
Now, cells are used to manage containerized applications within Cloud Foundry.
These are called Diego Cells.
They'll make sure to schedule with the application,
search that it's always running and available to our end users.
In the Routes, which is going to be the next service from Cloud Foundry,
we'll be able to see any endpoints which have
been provisioned for our application to reach it.
Currently, we have no routes provisioned since we have no applications deployed.
The following functionality is going to be the feature flags that we can
use to either enable or disable some functionalities using Cloud Foundry.
The Build Packs will provide the base framework we can use to build our application.
For example, if you use a Java application or Python application,
you'll be able to use a Build Pack package for that.
Just as a reminder, Build Packs doesn't use any docker files.
As such, we will be able to create an OCI compliant image by using
best practices and Build Packs can do that with no dependencies or configuration files.
In this year, for example, we see some of the predefined Build packs,
such as for a huge applications for Nginx,
for Java, Ruby, and many more and we'll be able to explore all of them in this view.
The stack functionality, if you click on it,
it will pretty much provisions something similar to an operating system.
Here, for example, we have a operating system which is based on Linux,
but with Cloud Foundry installed already in it.
We have a SUSE Linux Enterprise operating system,
in Version 12 and Version 15.
The next thing that I would like to showcase is the security groups.
Here we have something which allows us or tells the application to
reach endpoints and it will specify the protocol such as TCP or UDP,
the IP of the service and the port.
You'll be able to explore some of the pre-configured endpoints in the Service Groups.
The organization quotas.
These are pretty much all of the organizations that have been
provisioned by default and for example,
if I click on "Sandbox," we'll be able to see the same view we've seen
previously where it specifies the amount of memory we can use,
the amount of applications we can deploy and so forth.
Let's go back. The last thing I would like to showcase are the events.
The events are aggregated for the entire Cloud Foundry application.
So you'll be able to see if some of application were removed or
scheduled and so forth and you'll be able to
collectively see all of these events in this view.
With this particular offering of Cloud Foundry from SUSE,
we will further use to deploy an application such as Python HelloWorld,
and see how we can deploy and access it with minimal engineering effort.