In this demo, we will deploy a simple Python-helloworld application using Cloud Foundry.
We have already explored the Stratos console and the functionality it offers.
Now, let's deploy an application.
For that, we need to be in the application view,
and then we'll be able to see that currently,
we have no application is deployed.
However, we will be able to deploy an application by clicking the "Plus' button,
which is on the top right corner. Let's click that.
Here, we have multiple offerings that we'll be able to connect our code to Cloud Foundry.
We could reference a Public GitHub just to Git URL of
different registry and Docker Image or you can
even upload your code directly to this console.
For this example, we're going to use a Public GitHub repository. Let's click that.
Now, before we further configure any applications,
let's look into our Python-Hello World application.
Currently, this is a public repository which contains a helloworld application.
We can inspect our application which is in the app.py file.
Let's click that. Here, we have a flask application
which provides a collection of endpoints such as status,
metrics, and the main route endpoint which returns a Hello World message.
As well, our application currently is serving on port 8080.
If you could go back as well,
just to make sure that our application has a set of requirements,
and these are going to be, for example, flask,
making sure that we need to have flask up and running and being installed.
Let's go back to the main route.
Now, since we've explored our application,
we are ready to deploy it.
Going back to the Cloud Foundry console,
here we are able to select that we want to
have a Cloud Foundry project in a particular organization.
This is going to be the test account which have been
allocated to test and deploy in application.
Then we'll be able to choose a space.
Here, pretty much we have the development stages,
usually would have sandbox,
dev, staging, production, and many more.
For this demo, we're just going to choose the first one,
which is going to be dev. Then we click next.
Here we need to specify the GitHub project for our application.
Since it's a public repository,
is just enough for us to start typing your username.
In this particular case, I'm going to start my GitHub username, which is kgamanji.
Here I'm going to have a view of all the public repositories that I'm currently having.
We want to deploy our Python-helloworld application.
Let's select that. Here, we are retrieved
with the main URL for our project as well of any branches that we'd like to select.
For now, we'll leave it to the master branch. Let's click "Next'.
In this view, we'll be able to select a particular commit that we'd like to deploy.
For example, if we have a commit,
when we update it, for example,
the py.test, we'll be able to choose that particular commit to be deployed,
or we can always choose the latest one.
You always have the options to refresh your view of commits,
just making sure that you always have the latest commit if you'd like to deploy that.
We've selected it to the less commit.
In this view, let's click Next.
Here, we'll have an option to override or
provide any configuration for our Cloud Foundry application.
Now, before I'm actually completing a notice configuration,
let's go back to our Python-hello world application.
In this view, we actually have a manifest.yml.
A manifest.yml is very particular to Cloud Foundry.
We'll be able to provide some of
the configuration's code rather than configuring it in the console.
As such, when we instruct Cloud Foundry to deploy a particular application,
it will look for this manifest.yml file by default.
In this view, we create an application with the name python-helloworld.
We provide a value for our memory, in this case,
64 megabytes and we provide in disk_quota,
in this case 256 megabytes.
As well, since we are running a Python application,
we choose a python-buildpack framework to build our application.
If we can go back to our console,
we'll be able to override some of those parameters for example,
such as the application name or the quotas.
But we choose not to do so since we have that already in our configuration file.
If you scroll down, you'll be able to configure your routes.
In this particular case, I'm just going to select,
create a random route,
since I just want one random endpoint just to access and test my application.
Scrolling down, you'll be able to create,
or actually, we'll be able to choose a particular stack for our application.
The stacks are going to be the base operating system.
If we're scrolling down, even be able to customize
our buildpacks or provide a Docker Image and if a Docker Image is private,
you'll be able to provide a Docker username and password.
Unless we could configure, is the run command,
so how exactly your application should be started,
and the Health Checks?
I'll be able to either check an http endpoint,
a port, or run a particular process to check if your application is in the health state.
For that, you'll be able to choose the amount of seconds you would
like that health check to be implemented or called.
In this view, the only thing we've selected has been the create a random route.
We don't want to change any of the other configurations for now.
The last thing we need to do is to click "Deploy."
In this view, we already see that some of
the configuration has been picked up by Cloud Foundry.
For example, in this console,
we can see that the name has been picked up, what's being python-helloworld.
We have the buildpacks for Python to build our application.
We've got our disk and memory quotas already set
up and we already have a route being provisioned.
Soon as the application is deployed,
we'll be able to use this particular route to access the application.
Let's click on the go-to app summary.
This pretty much returns us to the application view.
Here we'll be able to see that our application is starting and
it will be up and running in a couple of seconds.
Let's explore offer options for our application.
Again, you'll be able to see the quotas that are set up for our application.
The build information such as the buildpacks framework,
the git commit as well.
If you'd like to choose a different commit,
you'll be able to visualize it here.
The application info such as how to start the application.
Here we invoke Python and app.py,
and we specify the port.
Actually, the port is going to be picked up automatically,
and here's going to be 8080.
If you would configure a health check,
you'll be able to visualize it here.
Now, if I do a refresh and scroll all the way up,
I can see that the status of my application
has been changed to deploy it and it's online.
Let's actually access it.
For that, we can click on the routes.
Here we see our endpoint.
If you click on this endpoint,
it will pretty much direct us to a running instance of our application.
Since it's a python-helloworld application,
it will return our helloworld message just as expected.
Let's go back to our console.
You'll be able to inspect the instances so if you click on the Instances tab,
you'll be able to see that we have one replica of our application.
Most importantly, you'll be able to see some of the memory, disk,
and CPU usage for this application,
which is always handy to understand the actual resources your application is using.
We can click on the Log Streams,
which will provide a console of all of the logs that are collected from our application.
In the services tab,
we will be able to see any services that have been integrated
with our applications such as databases.
Since we've configured none,
this view is going to be empty.
Then we'll be able to see an aggregation of events and more importantly metrics.
If you'd like to have a more insightful view of our CPU memory and disk,
you will be able to see that from the metrics view.
The auto-scaling functionality will allow us to scale up and down if
the customers have a high demand and there's a lot of traffic coming to our application,
but that you'll be able to create a policy.
The last thing I'd like to showcase is the GitHub functionality,
which will provide us with an interview of the deployment information.
For example, the year-old to our repository,
the branch, and the particular commit that we have been deployed.
As such, this is a very realistic example of how you'll
be able to deploy your application using Cloud Foundry,
but more importantly, with minimal engineering effort.
The only thing that you had to do in this particular demo,
was to upload or to even reference your source code,
and the deployment has been done for you in the background.