In this demo, we will explore
the cluster assets by using some of the predefined Kubernetes tail commands,
such as cluster info,
or getting nodes and describe nodes.
However, before we do that,
let's look into the kube config file,
which will allow us to query the clustering.
As mentioned, the kube config file is usually stored under
the.kube folder and in the config file.
If you look inside that particular file,
we'll be able to see all the necessary information metadata, to access cluster.
The first thing that we've learned,
is that we're going to have a cluster configuration.
Here we have a cluster with the name kind-demo,
which will authenticate or authorize
any users to access the cluster by using a certificate authority data.
As you can see, this is quite a lengthy input that we have here,
which has been already auto-generated.
Then we have the server,
or the API endpoint for Kubernetes.
Here this is running on the local host on port 61151.
The second thing that we require is to define a user.
Let's look into our kube config file for the user section.
Here we have a user with the name kind-demo as well,
and we authenticate this user by using a client certificate data.
We go down, we're going to have a client key data as well.
This will be used to make sure that the user
has the right permissions to carry the cluster.
The last thing we need to do,
is to link the cluster to user,
for that we're going to use a context.
Here we have a context,
which links the cluster with the name kind-demo, to user kind-demo.
Then we set the current context to be kind-demo as well.
Pretty much, we are going to use the current cluster and authentication
metadata to make sure that we can query and interact with cluster resources.
Let's exit the file.
Once we have a valid kube config file,
we'll be able to query the cluster.
The first thing we can do to find more information about all cluster,
is to looking into the main information provides.
That can be queried by using a kubectl cluster info command.
If you hit enter, you'll be able to see the endpoint for our Kubernetes master,
which is running on the local host on port 61151 and then we'll be able to see any atoms,
in this case, we have the KubeDNS,
which provides our DNS capabilities.
We're just going to run on local host on port 61151.
However, it's going to be a particular service within the cluster.
It's going to be a KubeDNS service.
The other thing we can do to query the clusters to identify the notes that we have.
For that, we issue kubectl,
get nodes command, which will list all the current nodes within the cluster.
We have a demo-control-plane note,
which is a master node and it's in a ready status,
which has been created just under one hour ago.
We can see the version of these particular note, which is 1.19.1.
To get more output or a wider output from this command,
we can use the -o wide flag,
which indicates that we want more information from all cluster.
Again, we're going to have the name of the note,
the status, its role,
which is going to be master,
the version of Kubernetes which is going to be 1.19.1 and we have the Internal-IP.
This is going to be pretty much the IP of the node.
Then we'll have the Ubuntu,
which is our OS image.
We can specify the kernel version,
as well the Container runtime,
which in this case is containerd,
running in version 1.4.0.
Once we have all nodes, we'll be able to actually have
a even more insightful output by using a describe command.
For that, we can use a kubectl describe command and
want us to get more information about our node and then we specify the name of the node.
You hit enter. This is going to be a very verbose output.
However, we'll have information such as the name of the cluster, any roles,
in this case master and your labels and annotations associated with it,
the time when it was created.
Then you'll have a series of events which
makes sure that we have our node up and running.
We have the address,
which is the internal IP and host name for all cluster.
We have more details about the capacity,
this is going to contain the CPU and memory that we have allocated for our node,
we'll be able to do dive into the system info,
such as the operating system version,
or the operating system image,
the current kernel version, and so forth.
As well, we'll be able to see the Kubelet version,
which in this case is 1.19.1.
But more importantly, we'll be able to identify the PodCIDR and this will be containing
the subset which will be used to allocate
an IP to the pods running on this particular node.
The last thing we can observe are the pods running on this particular node.
In this case, we can see that we have nine pods in
total and we'll be able to even look into those,
for example the namespace,
the name of the pod,
and the amount of CPU requests and memory requests it actual requires.
We can even have a more insightful output of
the allocated resources currently on this particular node.
We can see that 21 percent of the CPU amount has been
consumed and only nine percent of the memory amount has been consumed.
As well, the node description is going to be associated with a series of events,
for example if you schedule a pod in this particular node,
we'll be able to see this particular log or event recorded over here.