In this demo, we will deploy an application by using
Kubernetes resources such as deployments, ReplicaSets, and ports.
Before we do that, let's clear our cluster at the moment.
Let's look into the deployments that we have currently running.
For that, we're going to do a kubectl, get deploys comment,
which will return that no resources or no deployments are found in the current namespace.
Again, each of same command with the replica sets,
so kubectl get RS,
which is short for replica set,
and we have no resources as expected.
We can even get the ports.
Of course we have no ports currently running within the current namespace.
First of all, let's try to deploy
a go-helloworld application by using a deployment resource.
For that we're going to use, a kubectl create deploy command,
and then we can specify the name of the deployment in this case go-helloworld,
and then we can specify the image.
Since we already have created an image for our go-helloworld application,
we would just paste it here,
which is pixelpotato in the go-helloworld image inversion 1.0.0.
Let's hit "Enter " and this will create a deployment.
We can verify that by doing a kubectl get deploy Comand,
which will return that we currently have a deployment,
which is go-helloworld and we have a container,
but it's not yet ready.
We can look into the ReplicaSet,
so we issue a kebectl get RS command,
and we see that we have a ReplicaSet.
We've one desired port,
which is already running.
The last thing we can do is to get our ports.
So a kubectl get PORTS Command,
which will return older running ports.
Currently we have a go-helloworld port,
which is ready and in a running state.
To verify that our application is actually running inside the port,
we'll be able to use a port-forward command.
This will pretty much allow us to access the container from the local host.
Let's port-forward, or let's connect to our application within the container.
For that, I'm going to use a kubectl port-forward command,
where we need to specify the port that we want to connect to,
in this case, we're just going to copy the port name,
which is go-helloworld and hash for the ReplicaSet and the port,
and then we're going to specify in the port that we'd like to connect through.
Since our application is running on port 6111,
we will specify this port,
and then you're going to specify the port on the host that we'd like to connect through.
In this case is going to be 6111 as well.
We can choose a different port if you choose so now. Let's hit "Enter ".
Here we actually how that we are listening on the local host on port
6111 to the container port 16111.
Let's verify that we can connect to the container by going to the local browser,
and going to the local host on port 6111.
As expected, we get helloworld application from our container,
which means the application is up and running and it
returns the expected message to us as well.
Now let's update our application.
So far we have an application running within a port,
However, let's see how the rolling out strategy is happening.
For that, let's edit our deployment resource wave by using the kubectl edit command,
where we need to specify the deployment and deployment name,
in this case, go-helloworld.
Then we can specify the format we'd like the edit to happen in.
In this particular case, we choose YAML,
so we specify to output or to format this particular deployment in YAML.
Once we hit "Enter",
let's look for our image results.
Here we can see that we run an image the way we specified on the command line,
which is go-helloworld in version 1.0.0.
For that, let's update our image version to 2.0.0,
which is running on a different port.
In this particular image,
the application is accessible through porch 6112 instead of 6111,
and we'll be able to verify that.
Since we've changed the image version,
let's save the deployment.
The thing we need to do is to verify if we have a new ReplicaSet.
For that we do a kubectl, get ReplicaSets.
You see that we have a new ReplicaSet which was created 11 seconds ago and we can see
that already the port is running with this particular configuration.
If you do a kubectl get ports,
we will see that we have a new port up and running for 25 seconds,
so it has been created quite recently.
Let's port-forward into our application again, using port 6111.
We'll just need to change the port name since we have a different port a the moment.
We do a kubectl port forward into the port with
the name go-helloworld into the port 6111.
We hit "Enter", and then go back to our browser. Let's refresh.
Here you could see that it's hanging,
which means that after a while is going to time out and return an error.
This is because we've changed the port our application is accessible through.
Let's cancel this request.
We can actually see that we failed to connect to our port,
since we were trying to go in a different port.
We'll be able to connect our port by changing the port to 6112.
If we hit "Enter" and go back to
our browser and type or access the local host on port 6112,
we will have our helloworld message,
which pretty much is
the message that we expect from our application but on a different port,
since we're using a different image version.
This is pretty much how you are able to deploy an application, but more importantly,
how to have rolling updates to the image
and change different behaviors for our application.