In this demo, we will access an application by using a service Kubernetes resource.
For that, we can expose a deployment that we currently have
running on a particular port and access it from within the cluster.
First, let's look into the deployments that we currently have running within the cluster.
We're going to do a kubectl get deploy command.
Currently, we have a go-helloworld application which has one pod which is up and running.
It can even verify the pods by doing the kubectl get pod command.
We have one pod for go-helloworld application.
Before we deploy a service,
let's look into the current services that we have within our namespace.
For that, we're going to use a kubectl get svc,
which is short for services, then hit Enter.
We will have one service which already has been predefined for this cluster,
which is the Kubernetes service.
This is a predefined service which comes when the cluster is bootstrap initially.
Let's expose our deployment through a service by using the kubectl expose command.
Type kubectl expose, then we want to expose a deployment we've name, go-helloworld.
We need to specify the port and the target port as well.
The port will be the port that the service should serve on.
We say that this service should serve on,
for example, port 6112.
We can specify the target port,
which will specify the port that the application is listening to.
In this case, the application is listening to port 6112 as well.
We'll specify that for the target port and set it to a 6112.
If we hit Enter, we can see that a surface resource has been created.
We can verify that by doing a kubectl get svc command.
We can see that we have a new service which has the type ClusterIP,
which is the default type for a service if we don't specify one,
then we have the actual ClusterIP for our application.
Instead of accessing the pod independently,
we'll be able to access it by using the service IP.
In this case, 10.105.166.228.
Then we have the port the service is serving on.
In this case, it is going to serve on port 6112 using TCP,
which is the default network protocol for a service.
To verify that we can access our application,
let's first create a pod, a test pod.
Since we're using a Cluster IP,
that means that this particular IP is going to
be accessible only from within the cluster.
We need to access it from a workload which is within the cluster as well.
For that, I'm going to use a kubectl run command where we provide the name of the pod,
in this case, it's going to be a random name we created in the default namespace.
We're going to learn more about namespaces later on in this lesson.
Then we specify that we want to remove the pod once we exit from it.
We have an interactive shell as well.
We specify that this pod should run
the alpine image and then we'll be able to associate into it.
If we hit Enter to this command,
this will create a pod and provide us with an interactive shell straightaway.
The only thing we need to do is to access our workload.
For that, we use wget,
which is the equivalent of curl within the Bash commands.
We're going to have a quiet output.
We want the output to be presented into the current view.
The only thing we need to do is to provide
the ClusterIP and then we need to specify the port as well,
which is serving on, which is 6112.
If we hit Enter, we'll be able to receive the hello world message from our application.
This is pretty much how can we interact with our application by using a service IP.