Kubectl is the Kubernetes CLI,
that supports two different configuration management techniques,
imperative and declarative.
Within imperative approach, the operations are performed on
the live object in the cluster and is best suited for development phases.
It presents a low entry lever bar to interact with the cluster.
On the other side, the operations in
the declarative approach are performed on the manifest stored locally,
and it's recommended to use it in production systems.
However, at the same time,
this approach presents quite a high learning curve as
an in-depth understanding of the YAML manifest structure is required.
So far all the kubectl commands that you
have been learning are using the imperative approach.
You have created, interacted,
and manage resources directly on the live cluster.
For example, while creating the go-helloworld deployment,
we fear replicas in the test-udacity namespace.
You have used the imperative approach.
However, using command line arguments is not
suitable for some of the more advanced configurations,
such as readiness aliveness probes, or volume mountains.
To solve that vast configuration issue,
the YAML manifests were introduced.
The manifests encapsulate the full configuration for the covering
these objects where we can expand the definition and state of the resources.
This is done through YAML,
the data serialization standard of choice by the Kubernetes community,
and manifest structure consists of four obligatory sections;
API version, kind, metadata, and spec.
API version represents the Kubernetes API used to create an object.
Kind defines the object type to be created or configured.
Metadata stores the data that makes the objects identifiable,
such as name, namespace, and labels.
Spec defines the desired configuration state of the resource.
To get the YAML manifest of the resource,
use the kubectl get command associated with the dash or YAML flag,
which represents the output should be YAML formatted.
Let's explore a YAML manifests for a deployment resource.
In this example, we have the API version,
which is set to apps for slash v1.
Kind is deployment and in the metadata section,
we defined the name of the deployment, which is go-helloworld,
and the namespace it presides in,
here under test-udacity namespace.
Additionally, we said the labels for the deployment for example app equals go-helloworld.
Labels are powerful selectors in Kubernetes
that are used to identifying structure will deploy resources.
To create a deployment using a YAML manifest,
use the kubectl apply command.
This will require the path to the YAML file with
the desired configuration and it can be done by using the dash f flag.
In this example, we create a deployment defined,
indeed deployed at YAML file.
The deployment spec section can be split in free main areas.
The replica set configuration that will trigger the creation
of a replica set resource and define the desired amount of ports.
In this example, a replica set will be created to manage free pods.
The deployment configuration where the parameters for the rolling out strategy are set.
Copernicus currently supports two rollout strategies.
Recreate and rolling update.
Recreate will kill all existing pods before new ones are created,
and rolling update will update the pods in the rolling out fashion.
The last section is the container template where we can set the image,
image pull policy, name of the container, and many more.
In this example, we aim to an container with
the go-helloworld application in version 1.1.0,
a pull policy to download the image only when it's not available in
the host and container name set to go-helloworld.
However, in the container template,
more advanced configuration can be defined,
such as containerPort or the port that
the application is listening to and should be exposed for the container.
LivenessProbe, which is used to check if the port is up and running.
If the port is in an error state,
it will be automatically restarted.
ReadinessProbe, which is used to check if the application is
running inside the container and is ready to receive traffic.
Going back to the previous lessons,
when we talked about best practices to be adopted at the implementation stage.
One practice that focus on resource consumption.
Having awareness of the application boundaries for CPU and
memory is fundamental to ensure service availability 24-7.
This reduces the chances of an application to start when
CPU or be killed by insufficient memory capacity.
Once you have identified the application resource necessities,
this can be placed in the deployment manifest.
In the container template,
it is possible to define the resource requests,
which guarantees that the pod will be allocated with the request,
CPU, and memory values.
For example, in this case,
the go-helloworld container is requiring
64 mebibytes and 250 mini CPUs to run successfully.
Additionally, to ensure that the workload is not
consuming all of the available resources within a cluster,
the resource limits can be specified.
This ensures that the container cannot surpass the CPU and memory limits defined.
In this example, we limit the go-helloworld container to consume
no more than 128 mebibytes and 500 mini CPUs.
Now, let's explore how a YAML manifest for a service is constructed.
As expected, the service resource has the same four main required sections.
API version here is said to be one.
Kind which here is set to service.
Metadata, which will hold the parameters for the resource name, namespace, and labels.
Here, I'll meet it to make the output shorter and the spec section,
which contains the configuration for the exposed ports and service type.
In this example, we create a cluster API service that is serving on port
8111 and directs that traffic via TCP to the container on port 6112.
Kubernetes documentation is the best place to
explore the available parameters for YAML manifests.
However, you can easily construct a YAML template using kubectl.
This is possible by using the dry run and dash O YAML flags which instructs
the command should be validated on the client-side
only and output the result in YAML format.
For example, if you want to get the template for a deployment,
you need to use the create command and pass the required parameters.
Here we pass the name of the deployment, which is 'demo',
and the image that we want to execute,
here nginx, associated with a dry run and dash O YAML flags.
This will output the desired template that you can use
fervor to configure our YAML manifests.
Also, you can use the kubectl apply and delete to
create and delete resources which are defined for YAML manifests.