So far, you have learned that Kubernetes has a couple of methods
to handle failure any issue with application is healthy and accessible.
This is achieved through deployments with replica sets as it makes sure
that the desired amount of replicas are up and running at all times.
Readiness probes, which will ensure that traffic is
routed to pods that are ready to handle the requests.
Liveness probes that would check if the pod is
running and restart it if it's in an error state.
Services, which provide one entry point to all available part of an application.
With these resources properly configured,
the application will be in a healthy state unless
failure is encountered at the networking or DNS level.
Additionally, you have learned that the control plane is
composed of all elements that make global decision within the cluster,
while the data plane will host the workloads for multiple applications.
However, when it comes to failure scenarios,
one noteworthy thing is that the application is still going to
be up and running even if the Kubernetes control plane is down.
In this case, if one or all control plane components are compromised,
the traffic will still be routed to the application with no interference.
The downside of the control plane failure is that no new workloads can be
deployed and no changes can be applied to existing workloads.
The engineering team will still need to focus on
recovering the control plane as a critical priority.
However, they should not worry about recovering
applications as this will be intact and still handling requests.