In this demo, we will showcase how can we package an application using
Docker and using some of the commands we have been learning so far,
such as Docker build, tag, and push.
The aim of this demo is to dockerize a Python Hello World application.
For that, let's look first into the content of our folder.
If I list all the files I currently have,
there's going to be an app.py,
which will contain the main functionalities of our application,
requirements.txt, which will define the dependencies for our application,
and then we have a Dockerfile as well.
Let's start by looking into our app.py file.
If I do a vi app.py and we're just looking inside the application,
we can see it's a very simple Flask application that has a status,
metrics, and it has a main route or endpoint which will just return Hello World.
The requirements.txt, if we cut that particular file,
we'll have all the necessary dependencies to make sure that our application is running.
For example, we need to make sure that we have Flask installed,
so we will specify that as a dependency.
Now, once we have our application and requirements defined,
we'll be able to dockerize it.
Let's look into our docker file.
For that, I'm going to type vi Dockerfile and here we have
the content of what exactly we can construct our Docker image.
From label will specify the base image that we'd like to use to run our application.
In this case, since we have a Python application,
we're going to use a Python based image.
Here we specify version and it's 3.8,
so we're going to use the 3.8 version of the Python based image.
Label is used to just add metadata to the image,
such as the maintainer label and here we set it to Katie Gamanji.
The copy command is used to copy any files from the local host to the container.
In this case, we copy all the contents from
the current folder to the forward slash app inside of the container.
The second thing we do as well is to set the working directory to the forward slash app.
Pretty much all the future commands will be
run and executed from this particular location.
To make sure that the application has all the dependency is installed,
we use a pip command which will instill
any requirements we have in the requirements that takes the file.
The last thing we need to do is to specify how to start our application.
For that be used CMD command,
which specifies or instructs Python to run the app.py application.
Let's exit this file,
and since we have the Docker file,
the next stage for us is to build the image.
For that, we're going to use the Docker commands or a Docker CLI.
I'm going to do a docker version command,
so as a prerequisite for this course,
you should have Docker installed as well.
Here we have Docker inversion 19.03.13.
We'll be able to issue any Docker commands locally.
The other thing before we push our image,
let's look into Docker Hub.
Currently, I have a Python HelloWorld repository in Docker Hub where we will push
our image to be available for other team members or the community to use it.
Currently, if I look into the tags option,
I can see that I have no virtuous or no image pushed to do this repository.
We just have a clean repository and the main aim is to
push our Python HelloWorld image here.
To do so, let's firstly build our application.
For that, we're going to use the docker build command.
We will specify tag for our image,
so we're just going to specify it's a Python HelloWorld application.
Then we're going to specify the location of where our docker file is since we are
in the current directory with the application Docker file
and opcode and dependencies will specify the dot,
which pretty much means the current directory.
Hitting Enter, what this is actually going to do is going to
follow all the instructions from within the Docker file.
First of all, it actually downloads the Python in version 3.8,
so pretty much downloads the base image,
make sure it's available.
This depending on the size of image,
depends on the base image that you need to use is going to take an amount of time.
Once we have our Python base image,
then we'll follow the other instructions in the Docker file.
A such we'll copy all the files into the container,
will set the working directory,
install any requirements, and of course,
have a CMD command to start up our application.
Now, we've built our command,
will be able to see the image locally,
for that we can use the docker images command.
Where we can see that 24 seconds ago,
we've created our Python HelloWorld application and it has
an imaged ID and the tag is going to be set to latest by default.
We can actually test this particular application locally.
There's a way to test our image by using the docker run command.
We're going to use a docker run command,
we're going to use a detached mode,
meaning that the container should run in the background.
Then we can specify the port for our application.
Since it's a Python Flask application,
we use port 5,000 and we want to expose port 5,000 on the host as well.
The last thing remaining to do is to specify
our image which is going to be Python HelloWorld.
If I hit Enter, this will output the long ID of our container.
We can do a docker ps to
see all of the running containers at the moment and we can see that
we have a Python HelloWorld container that's running python dot app insight,
has been created 16 seconds ago,
and is exposing port 5,000 on TCP on the localhost.
We can test that easily by going into the local browser and just typing the localhost,
which is going to be 127.0.0.1 on port 5,000.
Hit Enter and we should see the Hello World message from our application.
At this stage, we have built our image and tested it.
The next stage is to target,
to be able to push it to Docker Hub.
Let's first tag our application.
For that, we use the Docker tag command where we specify
our Python HelloWorld image
locally and then specify the repository
and the image that we'd like to push to Docker Hub, including the version.
A tag is a very good method to version control different releases for our application.
In this case, we just send the version to 1.0.0.
If I hit Enter,
that will create a new tag for our image and we
can visualize that by looking into our images.
If we type a docker images command will be able to see that we
have a pixelpotato/pythonhelloworld with a tag in version 1.0.0,
but if you observe the imaged ID,
they going to be the same with our locally created image as well.
Since we have created our tag for the image,
the last thing is to push it to Docker Hub.
For that, we use a docker push command and we just
specify the long tag or the longer version for our image,
which will specify the repository in Docker hub,
the image name and version.
If I hit Enter, I expect to see an error and this is access denied.
Pretty much I need to login into Docker to make sure that I have
the right account and access to push Docker image.
For this, we're going to use a docker login command, hit Enter,
introduce your username, in this case,
pixel potato for me and the password.
I have logged in successfully,
which means now if I issue the docker push command again and hit Enter,
it will push all of the existing layers are pretty much our image to Docker Hub.
Cool. We have our image already pushed.
The last thing is to verify if it's actually available on Docker Hub.
Let's go back to our browser and look into
our HelloWorld repository within Docker Hub and if we look at the tags,
we can see that we have a new tag in version 1.0.0,
which was pushed just a few seconds ago.
This is pretty much how you'll be able to package,
tag and push an application to Docker Hub.
For you to use it forever you just need to pull it
or just specifying the longer version of the image,
including the repository, image name, and tag.
This is how all the engineers or the community will
be able to use this image for their purpose.