This video, will provide a solution to
the exercise which aims to containerize a Go application.
First of all, let's look into the insights of the current folder,
which is our application folder.
If you list the content,
you'll be able to see a Dockerfile,
README.md and main.go file.
First of all let's look into the content of our main.go file,
which will contain the functionality or the logic for our application.
If we look inside the file,
we'll be able to see that we have a simple Hello World application,
that will return a Hello World message on the main route, on port 6111.
The next thing, once we have developed our application,
is to look into the Dockerfile.
The content of the Dockerfile will contain all the instructions or steps,
to make sure that we can build our application and execute it when the container starts.
The first instruction is FROM,
which sets a golang,
or a Go-based image, for our application.
We're using an Alpine version,
which is a lightweight version for a Go-based image.
The second thing we do is to set the working directory,
so pretty much the location from where
all the fervor commands or future commands will be executed from.
Here we set it to /gosrcapp.
Then we copy all the existing content from the current directory on
the local host to the directory inside the container.
Since we said the WORKDIR to gosrc/app,
the contents are going to be copied within this path.
The next thing that we do is to build our application.
For that, to build a Go application we use the go build Command,
and then we can specify the output of our build.
So pretty much this will create a binary with a name helloworld,
which will contain the compiled code for our Hello World application.
Of course, we need to expose the port since our application is listening on port 111.
We can use the EXPOSE Command to specify this port as the main one for our application.
The last thing is to start our application at the container start.
For that, we just invoke our binary, or compiled binary,
which is helloworld, which we have created from our go build stage.
Let's exit this file.
Once we have our Dockerfile,
the next thing is to build an image for that.
To do so, we use the docker build Command,
and we can take our image,
to have it as a go-helloworld application,
and we specified the current path, or the current directory,
as the one which contains the Dockerfile and
any source code and dependencies for our application.
Let's hit Enter. I just have to use the right tag,
so -t is pretty much our tag Command.
As expected, this will download the goalpine image,
which is our base image for the application.
As expected, we need to download the golangalpine,
or the go-base image,
to our local host,
and on top of it we're going to run the instructions from the Dockerfile,
such as setting the WORKDIR,
coping the files from the local directory to the location inside the container,
and compile the code,
and start the application when the container starts.
To see our image,
we have to do a docker images Command.
Here, like we said, we have a go-helloworld application,
with the latest tag,
which has been created 32 seconds ago.
We'll be able to run our application by using the docker run command.
It's always good to test the behavior of our application
before it pushing to public image registry.
For that we can use the docker run Command.
We choose to run our container in a detached mode,
so it's going to run in the background.
Then we'll be able to set the port for our container,
which will want to expose on the host.
In this case, we use port 6111,
in both circumstances, and then we just need to
specify the name of our image, which is go-helloworld.
Let's hit Enter. The container has being started,
and we have a long id,
which has been output.
To see our newly created container we can do a docker ps,
which will list the latest created containers,
such as the go-helloworld application,
which runs the helloworld binary,
and exposed it on port 6111 from the container to the host.
We can verify that by going to our local browser,
and if we just enter the local host,
which is 127.0.0.1, on port 6111,
we'll be able to see our helloworld from our Go application.
Before we push our image to Docker Hub,
let's make sure that we have no tags available at the moment,
so we have just a fresh repository, which is go-helloworld.
If we click on the repository,
and if we navigate to our tags option,
we'll be able to see that we have no available tags,
so pretty much have no versions for our application.
Let's tag our application.
For that, we're going to use a docker tag command,
where we can specify the name of the image on the local host,
and the name of the image in which we reserve for Docker Hub.
As such, you're going to specify the Docker Hub repository,
which is going to be pixelpotato,
the image name which is going to be go-helloworld, and of course,
the version of the image,
which in this case is 1.0.0.
Let's hit Enter. We can verify the new tag by issuing a docker images Command,
and here we see that we have a new tag for the pixelpotato repository,
and of course, the version is going to be 1.0.0.
The last thing we need to do is to push our image Docker Hub.
For that, we use the docker push Command,
and we just need to specify the new tag that we've just created.
If you hit Enter, this will take all layers from the current image,
and push them to Docker Hub.
Cool. Our image has been pushed successfully.
The only thing that's remaining is to validate that by refreshing our text page.
Here we're able to see that a new image version,
in version 1.0.0, has been pushed just a few seconds ago.
Just pretty much l will be able to containerize any application using Docker,
including a go-helloworld application.