In this demo, we will install Argo CD into
our Key FS Cluster and access it through the UI.
First of all, currently,
I'm inside the vagrant box and I can interact with a cluster by using kubesctl.
For that, I'm just going to do a kubectl get node.
I have one master node which is up and running,
and I can even get the ports in all namespaces.
For that, I'm going to use the A plug.
Currently, I have only ports within my Kube-system namespace.
Let's install Argo CD.
For that, we can follow the guide of how to get started.
This particular command will create a new namespace with the name Argo CD,
and then it will install any dependencies it
requires to make sure that Argo CD is up and running.
We're going to copy this command.
Go back to our terminal and paste them.
So we can see a namespace has been created and then
we just need to install upper dependencies as well.
Now if we do the kubectl,
get ports in the Argo CD namespace,
we'll see that we have new ports created for Argo to start.
This is actually going to take a while for them to be in an up and running state.
Let's wait for Argo CD to have all the containers in a running status.
At this stage, we have all the Argo CD components up and running.
We have multiple components for Argo such as a Redis,
a server, a repo,
dex, and an application controller.
This has been already been provisioned for you and you
just need to wait for them to be in an up and running state.
The next thing to do is to access our Argo CD application.
Currently, we're running it in a vagrant box and we'd like to access it through
a web browser such as Chrome or Firefox.
For that, we'll need to expose our application to be
accessible from the vagrant box to our host machine.
Let's get all the services within the Argo CD namespace.
We can see that our Argo CD Server is exposed using a cluster IP,
which means it's going to be available only within the cluster using
this IP and is going to be available on port 80 and 443.
As we want to access our application outside of the cluster,
we can use a nodeport to expose Arg CD Server from the vagrant box to our host.
For that, I'm just going to copy the manifest
for this particular Argo CD Server and change it to a nodeport.
I'm going to get the service in the Argo CD namespace with the name
Argo CD Server and I would like to get a verbose output of it and click "Enter."
This will pretty much provide us with the entire spec for
our service that we can use and just modify the type of it.
Let's do that and let's edit our file,
and we will remove some of the fields that have been already pre-configured,
as these are not required for our manifest.
As such, we can remove our annotation.
We can remove the equation timestamp and
the manage field since these are appended when the object is created.
Within our metadata, we can have our labels with the name for the service,
which we'll mention as being a nodeport.
We leave our namespace,
which is going to be still Argo CD.
We can remove a resource revision since this is already appended.
The self-link and new ID can be removed as well.
We will remove the cluster IP as well since this has been
provisioned and added to this manifest when the cluster IP was created.
The last thing we're going to do,
we're going to change our type to NodePort.
Once we have changed our service type to NodePort,
then we just need to add the actual NodePort that we
can expose from our vagrant to our host.
For that, let's explore it a bit for our documentation for Kubernetes.
This is the main page for our service resource within
Kubernetes and we'll be able to explore how we can create
different types and particular capabilities
and functionalities of different service types.
The more important thing about the NodePort service type
is that we can allocate a port within this particular range.
It's going to be 30,000-32,767.
So we need to choose one port from this particular range.
The other thing we need to do, if we scroll a little bit down,
we'll see a YAML manifest for our service.
In addition to our manifest,
we need to add this particular nodePort.
Let's copy this and let's add it to our manifest.
What I want to do is to add a NodePort,
which for HTTP or port 80,
is going to run on 3007.
We can add the same thing,
but with a different port for HTTPS traffic,
just going to be secured traffic on port 3008.
Let's save that and let's apply this particular manifest.
For that, we're going to use kubectl apply referencing
our newly-created manifest for our NodePort service for Argo CD server.
Let's apply this. We can see that a new Argo CD server,
which is exposed using NodePort has been created.
We can verify that by doing a "kubectl get services" in the Argo CD namespace.
We see that we have the NodePort service,
which exposes our service on Port 3007 and 3008.
Cool. We have exposed it to the vagrant box so now we can access it from our machine.
The other thing I would like to showcase is that
currently our vagrant box has a static IP,
and we'll be able to visualize that in the vagrant file.
When we created our vigor file,
we allocated one particular IP.
So we'll access our vagrant box using this IP.
If we append the nodeport to this particular IP,
will be able to access Arg CD. Let's verify that.
If I'm going to IP we have,
and then we choose a port,
be it 3007 or 3008, click "Enter."
At this stage, you'll be prompted with an SSL warning.
This is because the Argo CD server is not set
up wave SSL certificates to authenticate a server.
Hence we establish an insecure connection and see the warning in the browser.
To simply access Argo CD just bypass this warning and you'll reach the login screen.
To connect to the Argo CD,
we need to use the admin credentials.
Currently, they have a way to give
the password and just copy this command which has been referenced in the exercise.
If you shoot, this will return us with pretty much the password,
which is just the name of the pod of the Argo CD server.
The username is going to be admin.
Let's login into our Argo CD server using the admin,
username, and the password that has been issued.
This is how we'll be able to authenticate and access
our Argo CD from within our vagrant box.