In this demo, we will create a helm chart to manage
the deployment and namespace resources for an application.
Then will use the at home chart,
and deployed using argo-cd.
Before we do so, let's explore our helm chart.
If I list all of the files I currently have in the directory,
I have a helm chart and of course,
I have the expected components such as a charted helm,
the templates folder, and devalues file,
wonderful prod, and a default values file as well.
Let's explore our charted helm file.
First of all, we provision a name for our chart,
in this case python-hello-world.
Then we have a short description of what exactly these helm chart is going to do,
in this case is just going to install a python-hello-world deployment.
Begin provision in keywords for a quick identification of what the chart does.
We have a version which here is said to 1.0.0,
and of course we can provide at list of maintainers,
their name, and the method of contact.
If we release the files in the template folder,
we'll be able to see the manifest for a deployment,
and a namespace, this are already parameterized,
which means that we can pass values to these manifests.
Let's explore the names-pace resource,
so we going to look into within the templates namespace.yaml file,
and here we have a namespace resource,
and we provide a name for our namespace,
but currently this is parameterized,
so we're going to take the name of the namespace from the values.yaml file.
If you look into the deployment manifest,
that's going to be parametrized too,
but we will parameterize different fields.
As such, we still parameterize the namespace,
so this is going to be set to a particular value from the values.yaml file,
and then we parameterize the amount of replicas,
and we can even parameterize the image,
so we specify an image repository,
and an image tag,
and thus component of our helm chart is going to be the values.yaml file.
Let's look into that. Currently, we have a default name for our namespace,
which here is going to be set to test.
For the image, we can specify the repository and
the tag parameters since these have been parameterized already using Go template.
As such the repository will point to the python- hello-world image and
the tag is going to specify the v point 1.0.0 version,
and for our deployment, we are parameterizing the amount for replicas,
which in this case is going to be set to three.
As you can see, we have provisioned a values.prod.yaml as well.
This can be used to overwrite some of the parameters for our helm chart.
Let's look into values-prod.yaml as well.
As you can see here, we only parameterize the name of the namespace and reset it to prod,
so instead of parameterizing all of the variables,
we just choose to overwrite the name of the namespace.
Let's deploy our helm chart by using an argo-cd application.
First of all, let us look into the Y for argo-cd.
As expected, currently we have no applications deployed yet.
Let's first deploy our application using the default values.yaml file.
For that, we need to create an Application CRD.
The Applications CRD is going to have a name set to python-hello-world,
and it's going to be deployed in the argo-cd namespace.
The destination section specifies that we want
to deploy the manifests in the current cluster,
and in the source will be able to reference our manifests.
Since we have a helm chart,
we're going to specify the location of our chart.
As such, the chart currently stored in
argo-cd-demo repository under the helm-python-hello-world path,
and we can even verify that by looking into the repo,
so within argo-cd-demo, helm-python-hello-world repository,
we have our helm chart,
we have been exploring just before this.
The last thing we need to specify,
especially when you're using a helm deployment for argo-cd is to specify the values file.
In this particular case, we specify the default values.yaml file to be used.
If you'd like to deploy the same application,
but using the prod as file,
we'll be able to do so by creating another Application CRD.
So if you look into the python-hello-world for prod deployment,
the configuration is going to be quite similar,
is going to be deployed within the same cluster,
using the destination configuration.
However, in the source,
we still specify that our chart is within the argo-cd-demo,
within the helm-python-hello-world folder.
However, we just change the values file in this case,
it's going to point to value-prod.yaml,
so it will create a namespace with the name prod instead.
Let's deploy both of these Applications CRDs,
for that we're going to use gives kubectyl apply - F, referencing our manifests.
This has been creating a simple python-hello-world application.
We can even verify that by going to our UI in argo-cd,
we can click on our python-hello-world and we see that we have a test,
and a deployment, and we'll be able to synchronize that as well.
Lets click on the "SYNC", and synchronize,
and this will create the test and the python-hello-world deployment.
Further, let's deploy our argo-cd, prod,
Application CRD as well,
and this will create a python-hello-world-prod application.
Going back to our UI,
we'll be able to see that we have now a prod version for our application,
and if you click on it, you will see that our namespace is already named prod,
so we already have been overwriting the values for our manifests.
Let's synchronize these resources as well by clicking on "SYNC" and synchronize.
As expected as this will create a namespace and a deployment wave, three pods as well.
The last thing we need to do is to verify these resources within the cluster.
Going back to our terminal,
we can do a kubectyl get namespaces,
and as expected, we're going to have a test namespace,
which is the default name for all the namespace which has been created a minute to go,
and we're going to have a prod namespace,
which was created under 20 seconds ago.
In fervor we can get pods in each namespace,
so if you look into the test namespace,
we're going to have three pos for python-hello-world,
and if we query the pods within the prod namespace,
we'll be able to see that we have three pos for our python-hello-world as well.
This is how you'll be able to template the configuration for
multiple environments by using one helm chart, but more importantly,
you'll be able to manage those and deploy those using argo-cd,
which makes the best of automatic reconciliation,
and identification of changes from within your get repository and manifests.