In this demo, we will use GitHub actions to
run some test for our Python-Hello World application.
First of all, let's look into our application which resides under the app.py file.
If you click on it and look inside,
we have a simple Python Flask application that presents us with a couple of endpoints,
such as: status, metrics,
and the main homepage which will return a "Hello World" message.
This application is running on port 8080 on the local host and when the container starts.
This application specifically has a set of
requirements which I'm going to be residing under the requirements that takes the file.
If we look inside, we will see some of
the dependencies the application will need, such as Flask.
Of course, we'll need pytest as well since we intend to
run some pytests on this particular application.
Let's go back to our main repository.
To implement any testing with pytests,
we'll actually require a suite of pytest being written beforehand.
In current case, we have a test_with_pytest.py file,
so pretty much of this will have all our tests if we look inside.
Currently, we have a mock test which will always return true,
so we have one test that will always succeed or will pass our test.
Now we'd like to run this particular pytest by using GitHub actions.
For that, let's go to our main directory which is python-helloworld.
We have learned that the GitHub actions are going to be
stored under the.github/workflows directory.
Let's click on it and look inside.
For this particular application,
we have a couple of GitHub actions being created.
Let's see how can we construct a GitHub action for our pytest.
This is going to be stored under the pytest.yml file.
Let's go for every single command and understand what it actually
does to run this particular GitHub action.
The first thing we do, we name our action to Pytest,
then we say when this particular action should run.
In this particular case, we say this action
should run on every push to our Git repository.
It's pretty much if you have a new commit,
and you commit and merge quite importantly,
this will run the GitHub action.
Then we have our Job sections,
and here we can specify the steps that we'd like to run in order to run our pytest.
First of all, we need to specify our base image or
the operating system that we're going to use to run our test.
In this case, we choose "Ubuntu-latest".
However, we have a strategy to run
our application or run our test on different Python versions,
such as: 2.7, 3.5,
3.6, 3.7, and 3.8.
The Steps section will contain the instructions to actually run the pytest.
The first thing we do is to check out our code.
Pretty much we'll take the current code with the new commit and reference it.
The second thing we do is to actually install Python,
I'm making sure that we have Python installed within our job.
For that, we use the setup-python action,
and then we have a for-loop to
implement or to set-up Python for every single version that we have.
Once we have set-up Python,
we need to make sure that we have all the dependencies necessary to run our application.
For example, we will update pip,
making sure that we have the latest version of our libraries.
Then we'll install pytest using pip.
The other thing we can do is to install the requirements
specified in the requirements that takes the file if that file exists.
After we install our dependencies,
we'll be able to run our pytest.
For that is just enough for us to invoke pytest,
it will identify the file with our tests and execute them.
Now let's actually execute this particular action.
I'm going back to our python-helloworld.
As mentioned, our action is going to be executed or
triggered with every commit to the master branch.
For that, I'm just going to edit the Read Me
page and I'm just going to add a comment saying,
this is a test.
I'm just going to commit this particular message to the Git branch.
We have a new commit,
that means that the GitHub actions will be triggered.
To see this particular event,
we can look into the Actions tab within GitHub. Let's click it.
In this view, we have a selection of GitHub actions we have set-up for this repository.
The one we actually are interested in is the Pytest,
so we're going to select that.
Then we'll be able to see some of the latest commits for our repository.
However, the one we are interested in is the commit with Update README,
since this will trigger the latest run of the action.
Let's click on the Update README,
which is the latest commit.
Here, we'll be able to see a summary of the GitHub action.
As such, you already can see
all the Python versions that we've intended to test our pytests.
We're going to have the version 2.7,
3.5, 3.6, 3.7, and 3.8.
Let's click on the build 3.8.
This will present us with a more verbose output of
all the events or commands that actually run.
We'll be able to see our checkout actions
which checked out to the entire code and if we expand,
for example, the Set up Python,
you'll be able to see how Python was installed on this particular job.
If you expand the Install Dependencies,
this will actually upgrade pip as intended.
However, it will install all the packages or dependencies in our requirements of txt,
including Flask and pytest as well.
To actually see the output of our pytest,
we have this Test with pytest output.
If we just expand that,
we'll be able to see that our test actually run and it passed as intended.
This is pretty much how you'd be able to run any test or more importantly,
how we can automate any tests with GitHub actions.