In this video, we're going to provide the solution to the exercise of how to
package in application or to dockerize it using GitHub action.
First of all, we have our Python Hello World image and
we'd like to push the latest version of our image to Docker Hub.
Before we deep dive into our application,
let's explore the tags we have currently in GitHub.
At the moment, for our pixel potato Python Hello World repository or image,
we have only one tag,
which is in version 1.0.0.
At the end of the solution,
you'll be able to see the latest tag within this view as well.
Let's go back to our Python Hello World application.
Currently, we have our main logic within the app.py, and if you could click on it,
we'll see a very simple application which presents a couple of inputs such as status,
metrics, and the main route,
which will just return a Hello World message to us.
Going back to our Python Hello World view,
we'll be able to see that we have a Dockerfile
which already has been presented with this repository.
If you click on the "Dockerfile",
this will contain pretty much all the main steps we need to containerize our application.
As such, we are going to use a base Python image in version 3.8.
We label our image,
copy all the content in the current repository to the.
/app inside the container.
Then we're going to set this particular repository /app as our working directory,
after which we will install all the requirements which are
presented in our requirements.txt file.
To start our container,
we will involve a cmd command,
which will just run our application by using Python.
Lets go back to our main view.
To create a GitHub Action,
which will containerize our application,
we will need to create it in the.github/workflows directory.
Let's look inside that directory.
Here we have already
a docker-build GitHub action which we'll will explore in more detail.
However, before we do that,
let's look into one of the predefined GitHub action
which will help us to build and push our Docker images.
This has been referenced in your exercise,
so you'll be able to follow the instructions here to easily dockerize your application.
This particular action is actually constructed of three main actions.
A login action which will authenticate you to GitHub get
help by using your credentials stored securely.
The setup-buildx, which will present
a more extensive CLI to build an application and setup-qemu,
which is able to execute on multiarchitecture containers,
and this is very useful when we have
applications using multiple libraries and frameworks.
If you can scroll a bit more down,
you'll be able to see some of the main usages of how
you'll be able to utilize these particular GitHub action.
You'll be able to reference this and reference it in
your GitHub action and to maybe build more complex use cases as well.
Let's go back to our GitHub action in the Python Hello World repository.
Let's look into our docker-build.yml.
Here we define our GitHub action with the name Docker Build and Push.
Then we have a condition which require us to invoke this particular action on
every push to the master branch or when
a pull request is created against the master branch.
In the jobs sections,
we specify the operating system that
we'd like to utilize in this case is going to be ubuntu-latest.
Then we're going to have a sequence of steps that will run to make
sure that we can build and more importantly, push our image.
The first line of couse, is going to be the action to check out our code,
so it will reference the existing code that we have with the latest creats.
We have set up QEMU,
which will create the execution environments for our containers.
Then we have Docker Buildx,
which will provide a more extensive interface to build our Docker image.
The next thing we do is to login into Docker Hub,
and for that we use the login action.
This is going to reference your username and password.
Your username and password are actually going to be
a your DOCKERHUB-USERNAME and the DOCKERHUB-TOKEN,
which you'll be able to create by using the reference instructions in the exercise.
Let's actually see how you can store your Docker Hub username and token.
For that, we can scroll all the way up and go to
the Settings tab of your repository. Let's click on this.
Here on the left panel,
you'll see the Secrets tab.
If you click on it, you'll be able to see
your current encrypted secrets that you can use securely for your actions.
As such, we have our GitHub Token,
which is going to be referenced from here,
and we're going to have our DOCKERHUB-USERNAME,
which again is going to be referenced from here.
You'll have an option to either remove or update those particular parameters.
Let's go back to our GitHub action,
scrolling all the away down.
Once you've logged in into Docker Hub,
of course the last thing is to build and push our image.
For that, we're going to use the Built and Push action,
which is already public and available for us to use.
We will set up the context which is going to be the current directory,
and then we're going to specify the location of our Dockerfile.
Since we have already Dockerfile provisioned,
we will just reference it.
The other thing we specify is that we'd like to create an image
which will be targeted to run on Linux machines.
Then you have a flag which is push,
meaning that if you'd like to push your Docker image to Docker Hub,
then you set it to true, otherwise it going to be false.
The last thing we do is specify a tag for our image,
pretty much where it's going to be stored, with what version.
In this case is our Python Hello World image is
stored in the pixel potato repository and Docker Hub,
and then will reference the latest version for this application.
Let's go ahead and actually execute our GitHub action.
I'm going go to the Python Hello World directory,
and I'm just going to edit the README file.
As we know, the GitHub action is going to be invoked on any push
or pull request that's going to be created against the master branch and for that,
I'm just going to remove this comment and submit the changes.
Let's go to our Actions tab,
and let's explore our Docker Build and Push action.
Here we have the Update README commit which we've just created. Let's click on it.
If we click on, our "Build",
we'll be able to see a more insightful or verbose output for
the actions that are taking place with these particular GitHub action.
As expected, we have a checkout which
will reference the code we currently have in the repository.
We'll set up QEMU, the Docker Buildx.
We already logged in into Docker Hub, which is great.
Our credentials were successfully referenced.
Then we have a build and push.
Let's go and extend the build and push stage.
This will present us with a more insightful overview of how
our application was built using the Dockerfile and how it's pushed to Docker Hub.
If you scroll up a bit more down,
we'll be able to see that we already referenced
the Python image that we choose for our base image in the Dockerfile,
and then we'll seek some of the instructions being followed,
such as the Copy command,
we'll be able to see our Working directory,
installing and your requirements using paper and so forth.
The end result of this particular action is to see
that we've actually pushed our image to Docker Hub.
Let's go back to Docker Hub view.
If you look into our Tags tab,
we'll be able to see that we have a new tag.
We've the latest tag all ready attached,
which was pushed a minute ago.
This is how you'd be able to build and push
your application to Docker Hub, but more importantly,
have a hands off process where
your build and push will be triggered when your marriage your code to the master branch.